טוב tov today's דף daf is ס"ז samech-zayin and dedicating today's דף
daf in memory of
יהושע שלמה בן מיכל זאב Yehoshua Shlomo ben Michal Zev it's a
20th
יארצייט yahrtzeit today and it's ערב שבועות erev Shavuot so let's get
going. The גמרא Gemara here we are on ס"ז עמוד א samech-zayin
amud aleph we just did the top line and it's dealing with
this issue about can ביטול bittul work. ביטול bittul can only work
when you already have sort of abstractly say when you already have
already a defined cohesive group which is in the גמרא Gemara at
least in the initial position of שמואל Shmuel both his position of
אוסרין osrin one person standing out makes a problem and מערבין me'arvin
you could choose to be מערב. me'arev. Okay and then the question
is what about if you have so you need both of those
criteria for ביטול bittul to work. What about if you have those
criteria but still it's considered separate like it's מחצר לחצר. mechatzar lechatzar.
So according to one version אביי's Abaye version of שמואל Shmuel that
would be okay. One חצר chatzer to another made a problem was
אוסרין osrin then it's enough to be one but according to another
opinion in the גמרא Gemara רבא Rava no on that is not
good actually that as long as it's מחצר לחצר mechatzar lechatzar it
cannot work. And I should also mention that there's a position that
completely rejects שמואל Shmuel which is who was it רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan who says you can't do ביטול מרשות לרשות. bittul me'reshut lereshut.
So these are all the questions of the various parameters. Anyway the
גמרא Gemara said that even if in general you can't do it
מחצר לחצר mechatzar lechatzar you can do it in the case of
where it's really you don't even really need ביטול bittul so much
you can do it in the case of you have two חצרות
chatzerot here again let's do this your A and your B. I
might have added A and B differently last time but okay which
is quick. Anyway here's your רשות הרבים reshut harabim or whatever you
have here anyway so in this case where you actually have a
joint עירוב eruv and
but one of the people forgot. So you have a joint עירוב
eruv and the עירוב eruv here is put in A and it's
the joint עירוב eruv and in that case one of these guys
forgot. I'm sorry no one of these guys forgot in B so
they're making the problem the עירוב eruv is in A in that
case A can be A can just be fine and ignore B
and it works for A itself. And so that would be okay.
If the guy in A however forgot it wouldn't be okay because
even though he's doing ביטול bittul again because they're all together in
the עירוב eruv it's a problem of ביטול מרשות לרשות. bittul me'reshut
lereshut. But here you don't even like you don't even need ביטול
bittul you just ignore B you've got the עירוב eruv B is
the problem you're fine. However if גמרא Gemara frames it as this
is would be a case where even if normally you don't have
ביטול מרשות לרשות bittul me'reshut lereshut you can because what B still
has to do all of B not just the guy that forgot
is basically waive their participation in the עירוב. eruv. As long as
they maintain their participation in the עירוב eruv the fact that they've
got a problem here creates a problem for A but they are
מבטל mevatel their right in A they waive their participation and that
lets A get along with their life. Okay so that's where we
ended up with yesterday and the גמרא Gemara just has one final
statement about that. Let's take a look.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says okay so I'll just
read I'll read from the very top of ס"ז עמוד א. samech-zayin
amud aleph. שכח אחד מן החיצונה ולא עירב Shachach echad min hachitzonah
velo eirev if one of the guys from B forgot the outer
courtyard ודאי פנימית מותרת vadai pnimis muteres then A can be okay.
דאחדה דשא ומשמשא De'achda dasha umishamsha it basically slams its door and
conceptually not literally and it can use its own courtyard okay and
therefore B is the
problem so they can cut off B and conceptually that's a case
where ביטול bittul can work מרשות לרשות me'reshut lereshut even if normally
you resist it because all ביטול bittul there means is that B
waives its rights to the עירוב. eruv. Okay וחיצונה אסורה vachitzonah asurah
and B remains forbidden. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרבא
Amar leh Rav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua leRava so רב הונא Rav
Huna the son
of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua said to רבא Rava דכי שכח אחד
מן הפנימית ולא עירב אמאי שתיהן אסורות dechi shachach echad min hapnimis
velo eirev amai shteihen asurot he says I don't get it why
even if it's the guy at A that forgot is it a
problem? Now we say it's a problem because since the problem is
here A has he has to do ביטול bittul in order for
this עירוב eruv to
work but since this עירוב eruv includes
B and B is part of you since the עירוב eruv includes
B so therefore you can't cut off B B isn't the problem
so therefore for this ביטול bittul to work he would have to
be מבטל mevatel not just to the members of A but also
to the members of B and you can't do that because אין
ביטול מרשות לרשות. ein bittul me'reshut lereshut. That's the way the גמרא
Gemara explained it yesterday. So he says I don't get why it
can't work. I'm going to show you how it can work. Why?
לבטיל בר פנימית לפנימית livatel bar pnimis lipnimis let the A guy
just be מבטל mevatel to his A friends ותיפוקי חיצונה ותשתרי בהדייהו
vetipoki chitzonah vetishtari bahadeihu and let B automatically become permitted. Meaning what
he says is like this conceptually okay it starts really with A.
The עירוב eruv is in A you're a member of A the
problem is in A so just say hey guys I'm מבטל mevatel
to you you guys have rights to use my courtyard okay ignore
B but then how could you ignore B B... Is part of
the עירוב. eruv. So he says no, because what happens is once
you've done—he believes that once you've done ביטול bittul to one of
the members of the group, it automatically works for everyone. You don't
have to knock on everybody's door. I'm also being a little, you
know, conceptual, but effectively say, I'm מבטל mevatel to you and I'm
מבטל mevatel to you and I'm מבטל mevatel to you and I'm
מבטל mevatel to you. Just מבטל mevatel to one and then it
works for the whole group. Okay, especially in this case where they're
already joined by an עירוב eruv but he's got the problem. So
you're
מבטל mevatel to your חצר chatzer which works and automatically the other
courtyard gets included, okay? And since you can primarily focus on your
courtyard because that's where the עירוב eruv is and that's where the
problem is, so you're allowed to focus, you do the ביטול bittul
here and then the other gets schlepped along. So who needs to
do an active ביטול bittul מרשות לרשות? me'reshus le'reshus? That's the question.
Okay, so the answer back is כמאן, ke'man, who are you saying
this? כרבי אליעזר. ke'Rabbi Eliezer. Your suggestion would work according to רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר אינו צריך לבטל רשות לכל אחד ואחד. de'amar
eino tzarich levatel reshus le'chol echad ve'echad. You don't have to be
מבטל mevatel to every individual. So you say the problem's in A,
the עירוב eruv is in A, focus on A and everything will
happen automatically. No, I say כי קאמינא, ki ka'amina, when I'm talking
and I'm saying that that's a problem that you have to—you have
to directly do it to B and you can't because it's מרשות
לרשות. me'reshus le'reshus. So that's לרבנן. le'rabbanan. I'm talking according to the
Rabbis דאמרי צריך לבטל לכל אחד ואחד. de'amri tzarich levatel le'chol echad
ve'echad. You have to be מבטל mevatel to each individual. So in
this case, because B is in the עירוב, eruv, you would have
to be מבטל mevatel to B and you can't because they are
not part of the group, it's מחצר לחצר. me'chatzer le'chatzer. And the
only case that works is if the problem is B and then
you just cut off B. Okay, so this is the most restrictive
approach that ביטול bittul only works when it
is אוסרין ומערבין osrin u'mearvin is not enough, you need it literally
to be one courtyard in order for ביטול bittul to work. And
the only case that ביטול bittul works is a case where effectively
you're just cutting them out. Okay, yes.
I don't really understand exactly what ביטול bittul is because—Join the club.
Yes. Because if you're—I don't understand the position of the רבנן rabbanan
if I'm מבטל mevatel to you and you're part of the עירוב
eruv then shouldn't it transfer to the entire body?
Yeah, I mean,
the—but—look, I don't understand it enough either. I mean, in this case
though, while on the one hand you have an עירוב eruv so
you can consider them a cohesive unit, the עירוב eruv isn't right
now operative because of the outlier. So first of all, that's one
issue, how coherent are they right now before the ביטול bittul has
taken effect? You know, that's one issue. The other—but you are right,
look, it is true that when you have a working עירוב eruv
they operate as a group like the thing we discussed before, which
is that if you're courtyard A and you take your עירוב, eruv,
one guy moves it over to B representing the entire group and
then it works for all of B. But that's when you're actually
taking the physical עירוב eruv which represents everything and the עירוב eruv
is already functioning. So my short answer besides that I agree I
don't really understand ביטול, bittul, but my short answer is that here
at least the עירוב eruv is already, you know, the עירוב eruv
isn't functioning because of your outlier and you need the ביטול bittul
to be effective to make it function. Yes.
One is, let's say they never made an עירוב eruv and I
want to מבטל. mevatel. Can he—if there was a door, can he
actually close it and say that's
it, I don't need it? It sounds
like—it sounds like no.
I don't know. It sounds like no. It sounds like their participation
because even if A were to close the door, right, if there
weren't a problem with the עירוב eruv and B could climb over
the fence or whatever, they'd be allowed to do it, right? They
are part of the עירוב eruv still. So it does sound like
you need the actual ביטול. bittul. Yeah.
The other question is instead of going through this every שבת, Shabbos,
can I just say, all right, you know, just assume you always
have rights to my—I'm always מבטל. mevatel. You know, whatever it is.
Always part of your עירוב. eruv. No. The problem so okay so
the problem with ביטול... bittul... always part of your עירוב eruv is
what we do. We just do a one thing and we leave
it that way and we forget about it and we say, you
know, it works for the whole year or whatever. And what's actually
going to be funny because we're going to have a case later
today where it sounds like they didn't do an עירוב eruv and
you sort of like wonder like why didn't—you know, it doesn't take
any effort, why don't you just do it although again maybe if
they don't have fresh bread it does take a certain amount of
effort, but why don't they use something like a מצה matzah and
be done with it? I don't know. Anyway, but yes, the ביטול
bittul issue though is that ביטול bittul as we've seen primarily is
for use when you're stuck on שבת, Shabbos, which is also why
we're limiting sort of it, you know, as a real sort of
like fiction. And ביטול bittul does not—is not fully—in this case ביטול
bittul is fully effective but in most cases like where a courtyard
and I forgot to participate. And I'm going to
be מבטל mevatel my רשות reshus to you guys on שבת, Shabbos,
the effect is is that I can't take out from my house
into the courtyard. So you actually because if I were to take
out from my house in the courtyard, it would conceptually reassert my
property rights and annul the ביטול. bittul. Okay. And the nature of
the ביטול bittul is basically I'm removing myself from here. So ביטול
bittul is not as effective as an עירוב. eruv. You don't want
to have to do ביטול, bittul, you want to do— No,
you can say okay let's say you didn't ever take an עירוב.
eruv. I'm away that week. I won't really care if I can't
take out from my house to the courtyard because I'm not going
to be there anyway.
You could be but we basically פוסקין poskin we basically פוסקין poskin
that if you're not there you don't participate in the עירוב eruv
anyway. So yes.
Since I'm your neighbor I can go into your house and bring
it out into the courtyard for you.
No. No, you cannot. It's not about me. That's a good point.
It's about my domain. So the things, even if you don't make
an עירוב, Eruv, the vessels that started שבת Shabbos in the courtyard
can be moved in the courtyard. And that started שבת Shabbos in
my house can be moved in my house. In your house, your
house. That's without an עירוב. Eruv. What an עירוב Eruv lets you
do is move courtyard vessels, I'll call them that, you know where
they started שבת, Shabbos, courtyard vessels into a house and house vessels
into a courtyard. So if I'm not part of it, oh actually
you're right, I'm sorry, because once I do ביטול, Bittul, the basic
problem is about me sort of reasserting my property rights. So if
it's actually you that's taking it...
yeah... I need to double-check that. I'm pretty sure you're right about
that. I need to double-check that. Yeah.
A always has the right of egress through B.
Yeah, it's never about walking, it's never about access, it's all just
about moving the vessels. Right. Okay, so let's now continue in the
גמרא. Gemara. Sounds like this. What kind of vessels are they talking
about?
Do they mean like work vessels or as we discussed before...
No, it doesn't matter what type of vessels. It's all about issues
of relating to conceptual carrying. Okay, even though it's not actually רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim.
Yeah,
that's a good question. Like somehow the word travels. You know, maybe
one guy said, oh my gosh, I forgot to make the עירוב
Eruv and then they find out. If they don't find out, it's
like a lot of things. You don't find out there was a
problem and you went ahead and you acted based on certain assumptions.
You know? All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. רב חסדא
ורב ששת. Rav Chisda ve-Rav Sheshes. This is a great little sort
of intro, although it doesn't exactly carry through. רב חסדא ורב ששת,
Rav Chisda ve-Rav Sheshes, כי פגעי בהדי הדדי, ki paguei bahadi hadadi,
when they would bump into one another, רב חסדא מרתען שפוותיה ממתניתא
דרב ששת. Rav Chisda martzin sifvosei mi-matneisa d'Rav Sheshes. רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, his lips would tremble because of the ברייתות Braisos of רב
ששת, Rav Sheshes, which means that רב ששת Rav Sheshes was a
big בקי Baki and knew like tons of משניות Mishnayos and ברייתות.
Braisos. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda would always start getting very anxious
when they were bumping into each other and that they were going
to have a halachic discussion that רב ששת Rav Sheshes was going
to quote some ברייתא Braisa or whatever and show him up. So
his lips would start trembling. רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, now רב ששת
Rav Sheshes on his side, מרתع כולי גופיה מפלפולא דרב חסדא. marta
kulei gufei mi-pilpulei d'Rav Chisda. His entire body would tremble because of
the sharpness of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. So you know, this is
the classic sort of dichotomy that the גמרא Gemara has between סיני
Sinai and עוקר הרים. Oker Harim. Right? The person that knows everything
and which is particularly significant in a time when there's no books.
So you really like, it's not just you can pick up, you
know, it's like that's how you have access to the information is
that you know it בעל פה ba'al peh as opposed to the
person that has great analysis. So they would be afraid of one
another. Okay. Now, בעא מיניה, ba'ei minei, so you're expecting a story
where one of them has real sharpness and the other quotes a
משנה Mishna or ברייתא. Braisa. Let's see where the story goes. בעא
מיניה ba'ei minei
רב חסדא מרב ששת. Rav Chisda me-Rav Sheshes. רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
the one who is supposed to be the, you know, who was
like the sharp analytical one asked from רב ששת. Rav Sheshes. שני
בתים משני צידי רשות הרבים. shnei batim mishnei tzidei reshus harabbim. You
have two houses on two sides of the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
which you can never make an עירוב. Eruv. It's two sides of
the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. ובאו נכרים והקיפום מחיצה בשבת. ubau nochrim
vehikkifum mehitzah beshabbos. And non-Jews came and they basically put a wall
around the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim on שבת. Shabbos. So they turned
it into רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. And a מחיצה mehitzah made on
שבת Shabbos counts. So it's now רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. But there's
no עירוב Eruv to it. Right? Because they didn't join together from
beforehand.
So מהו? mahu? What's the story? So you can't make an עירוב
Eruv on שבת, Shabbos, but we know what you can do is
you can do ביטול. Bittul.
So can you do ביטול Bittul in this case?
אליבא דמאן דאמר אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר. aliba d'man d'amar ein
bittul reshus michatzer l'chatzer. According to the שמואל Shmuel approach we were
discussing, which you can't do ביטול Bittul from one חצר chatzer to
the other because they basically have to be effectively like one domain.
So
לא תיבעי לך. lo tibailech. That's, I don't have to ask. That's
obvious. השתא דאיבעו לערובי מאתמול מצו מערבי, hashta d'iba'u le'arvei m'atmol matzu
me'arvei, if you say that when the case of one courtyard, you
know courtyard A and courtyard B, that in theory it was a
case of מערבין, me'arvin, meaning they could have joined together as one
courtyard and nevertheless you're saying that because they're separate courtyards the ביטול
Bittul does not work, even when in theory they could have been
מערב. me'ariv. So remember, this goes on the theme that אוסרין ומערבין
מבטלין. oserin u'mearvin mevatlin. That if you could have made an עירוב
Eruv and if you make problems for the other guy, that's enough
to say you're one courtyard, you know, you're one unit and you
can do ביטול. Bittul. So here in the case of courtyard to
courtyard, you know, let's say it was not a case of אוסרי,
osrei, right? It was the other case of courtyard to courtyard where
you have them that was like this but they had equal access
to the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Right? So that was a case
of מערבין ואין אוסרין. me'arvin v'ein oserin. Right? And that according to
שמואל Shmuel is you can't do it מחצר לחצר michatzer l'chatzer because
they do not create problems for one another. But in theory they
could have been מערב me'ariv together. So if when they could have
been מערב me'ariv together you still say
אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר, ein bittul reshus michatzer l'chatzer, so השתא...
where were we... הכא דלא מצי מערבי. So this case that when
שבת Shabbos began they couldn't have... the two houses done an עירוב
eiruv because it was רשות הרבים reshus harabbim when שבת Shabbos began.
מעצמו me'atzmo ביטולי נמי לא מצי מבטל. bittulei nami lo matzi m'vatil.
So they're certainly not one unit and they can't do ביטול. bittul.
עוד דילמא לא שנא Ode dilma lo shna or maybe that doesn't
make a difference. Okay, which is a pretty funny, but not really
as articulating what the what the reason would be. But okay fine.
So that's one die. One minute. One minute. עוד לא שנא. Ode
lo shna. So he says like this: Did I skip a line?
Yeah I skipped a line. I'm sorry. I skipped a lot of
lines. Okay right. So let's go back. I knew that it wasn't
making sense. אמרת אין ביטול Amarta ein bittul so let's go back.
אליבא דמאן דאמר אין ביטול
רשות מחצר לחצר לא תיבעי לך. Aliba d'man d'amar ein bittul reshus
mechatzar l'chatzar lo tiba'i lach.
If you can't go from A to B, I have no question.
השתא דאתו לערובי מעצמו מצי מערבי, Hasha d'vatu l'eruvay me'atzmo matzi m'arvi,
אמרת אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר. amarta ein bittul reshus mechatzar l'chatzar.
If when they could have done it together, they're still not enough
of a unit to do ביטול מחצר לחצר. bittul mechatzar l'chatzar. הכא
דאתו לערובי מעצמו לא מצי מערבי, Hacha d'vatu l'eruvay me'atzmo lo matzi
m'arvi, here where they couldn't have done it when שבת Shabbos began,
כל שכן, kol shekein, of course they can't do it together, okay?
So if you say that that, you know, that even if מערבין
m'arvin is not enough, you need like אוסרין ומערבין, osrin um'arvin, so
מערבין m'arvin is not enough and he and that's not enough of
a unit, so here when you couldn't have done done עירוב eiruv
from before שבת Shabbos there's no question you can't do ביטול. bittul.
כי תיבעי לך Ki tiba'i lach who's my question: אליבא דמאן דאמר
יש ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר. Aliba d'man d'amar yesh bittul reshus mechatzar
l'chatzar. According to the position not שמואל, Shmuel, which is the one
we've been focusing on, but the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that says A you can do ביטול bittul from A to B
even if it's not אוסרין, osrin, that you can do. התם דאתו
לערובי מעצמו מצי מערבי, Hasam d'vatu l'eruvay me'atzmo matzi m'arvi, ביטולי נמי
מצי מבטל. bittulei nami matzi m'vatel. So do we say the reason
you can do from A to B is because they could have
done an עירוב eiruv yesterday? אבל הכא דלא מצי מערבי מעצמו ביטולי
נמי לא מצי מבטל, Aval hacha d'lo matzu m'arvi me'atzmo bittulei nami
lo matzu m'vatel, or but here because they couldn't you cannot? עוד
דילמא לא שנא Ode dilma lo shna or maybe it doesn't matter.
So meaning, this case, right, where this is a case of
מערבין באין אוסרין, m'arvin b'ein osrin, right, because A doesn't create problems
for B. So that was a case about, you know, that according
to שמואל Shmuel they're not enough of a unit because of אין
אוסרין. ein osrin. So שמואל Shmuel would say no ביטול bittul because
אין ביטול מחצר לחצר ein bittul mechatzar l'chatzar and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan would say ביטול bittul because even in this case where they're
not unified he says יש ביטול מחצר לחצר. yesh bittul mechatzar l'chatzar.
So the point is like this: In this case if according if
you can't do ביטול bittul here even though you had the potential
of doing מערבין, m'arvin, then certainly you can't do it when you
got a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim turning into a רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid at שבת. Shabbos. There is no way where they were considered
to be unified. Okay and here you hear even one way is
not enough, certainly when there's no way that they're unified it's not
enough. But according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it works, why
does it work according to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Is it because
he at least has one criteria that makes them a unit, the
מערבין? m'arvin? Or maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't even care? רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says anytime ביטול bittul you can do ביטול bittul
anyway anytime that it'll help you can always do ביטול. bittul. Okay
so that's the question. According to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says
that works, is it important that they were able to be מערב
m'areiv yesterday or would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan always say you could
do ביטול? bittul? So that's one question. עוד דילמא לא שנא. Ode
dilma lo shna. Now remember by the way the reason this is
also relevant is because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan also said that you
could be מערב m'areiv בחורבה, b'chorva, right? Remember it's not just a
debate of conceptually being one unit. It's a it could be a
general debate about how strict are you about this idea of ביטול.
bittul. Because because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was also right שמואל Shmuel
was the one that said, you know, you cannot also remember the
discussion of the backyard? Can you do ביטול bittul in a backyard?
That has nothing to do with this conceptual issue of being one
unit. And still שמואל Shmuel was more strict and said no and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was more lenient and said yes. So that's
essentially what he's asking. When רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says yes is
it because he considers it one unit because of מערבין? m'arvin? Or
maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is just basically lenient about this and
doesn't mind doing ביטול, bittul, ביטול מחצר לחצר bittul mechatzar l'chatzar regardless.
So here too he would allow you to do ביטול bittul even
in this new scenario. That's the question. So let's see what the
answer is. So עוד דילמא לא שנא. Ode dilma lo shna. אמר
ליה
אין מבטלין. Amar lei ein m'vatlin. Sorry, that won't work. Even according
to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that's not enough to define them as
a unit, you know that's not enough. You need something to define
them as a unit so this would not work. Okay, I have
another question he said. מת נכרי בשבת מהו? Meis nochri b'shabbos mahu?
Let's say the non-Jew died on שבת. Shabbos. Now according to תוספות
Tosafos it's the special case where the non-Jew showed up on שבת
Shabbos and created a problem and then he died. Okay? So when
he showed up if you remember yesterday what do you have to
do when he showed up on שבת? Shabbos? You have to rent
from him. But because him showing up ruined the עירוב eiruv you
then have to do ביטול. bittul. Let's say he showed up and
then he died. So his showing up his you didn't do anything.
His showing up ruined the עירוב eiruv and now he died. So
now maybe just you can just do the ביטול bittul and you're
fine. Okay? It's assumed that you don't go back to where you
were before it began. Okay, so what happened? אליבא דמאן דאמר שוכרין
לא תיבעי לך. Aliba d'man d'amar sochrin lo tiba'i lach. According to
the... according to the one that says that when he was still
alive you could rent from him, then fine, there's no question, because
הכא תרתי עבדינן hacha tartei avdinan if when he was alive you
could both rent from him and then do the ביטול, bittul, חדא
מיבעיא chada mibaia here that now he's died, of course you can
just do
the
ביטול. bittul. אלא כי תיבעי לך Ella ki tibai lach what's my
question? אליבא דמאן דאמר אין שוכרין. Aliba deman de'amar ein sochrin.
Okay, according to the one that says that when he shows up
on Shabbos you can't do this, you can't rent from him and
then do ביטול. bittul. תרתי הוא דלא עבדינן? Tartei hu delo avdinan?
Is the problem that you can't do both, rent from him plus
the ביטול? bittul? הכא חדא עבדינן? Hacha chada avdinan? But if he
now has died you can just do the ביטול bittul and be
fine with it? או דלמא לא שנא? O dilma lo shena? Or
maybe it doesn't matter? אמר ליה, Amar lei, אני אומר מבטלין, Ani
omer mevatlin, והמנונא אומר אין מבטלין. VeHamnuna omer ein mevatlin.
He says, okay, I have that debate with Rav Hamnuna. I say
that case is okay, and Rav Hamnuna says it's no good. Now
I gotta tell you, okay, these were interesting final questions about these
scenarios of ביטול, bittul, but it's like it didn't work with the
setup, right? I mean, maybe this is פלפולא דרב חסדא, pilpula deRav
Chisda, although it's not at least so מפלפל mepalpel I don't think,
it's just you know, an interesting other scenario. Maybe it's מפלפל mepalpel
in the sense that it's like a crazy hypothetical. But a non-Jew
made a wall around here. He showed up and then he died.
Okay, but that's not normally what you expect from פלפולא pilpula that
it's just interesting hypotheticals. Conceptually it's not a very new type of
a question. And what's also interesting is that Rav Pappa didn't, Rav
Sheshes didn't come back with any משניות mishnayos or ברייתות. beraisos. So
I gotta tell you, he just gave him sort of like, look,
it doesn't work. Yeah, I say it does, you know, and Rav
Chisda and who was it and Rav Hamnuna, Rav Hamnuna says it
doesn't. So it's very strange, you know, about that. But maybe it
does also reflect the idea that if Rav Sheshes is such an
expert in משניות mishnayos and ברייתות, beraisos, you know, for him it's
more about this sort of apodictic. It's more about just bottom line.
Here's how I hold, here's how he holds. He doesn't even respond
in terms of, and maybe that's really the message I'm just thinking
now. He doesn't even respond in terms of the conceptual argument. Right?
He doesn't want to get into a discussion with Rav Chisda about
arguing it conceptually which one way makes more sense, because he maybe
knows Rav Chisda will best him in that discussion. So he just
takes the easy way out. He gives you bottom line. I don't
want to discuss the שקלא וטריא. shakla vetarya. Here's bottom line: yes,
no, end of story, let's move on. That's probably the point of
that of the story. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: נכרי
שיש לו פתח ארבעה על ארבעה. Nochri sheyesh lo pesach arba'ah al
arba'ah. Okay. So now you've got the non-Jew, you can see the
גמרא Gemara have like a lot of fun with this. You have
one little הלכה halacha that a non-Jew creates a problem in a
courtyard and you have all this גמרא Gemara like talking about different
scenarios. Okay. So you have this non-Jew that's creating the problem, but
he's got his back door. He's got a small little opening, four
טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim in his back door, פתוח לבקעה,
patuach lebik'ah, and it opens up into a valley. אפילו מכניס ומוציא
גמלים וקרונות Afilu machnis umotzi gemalim vekeronos כל היום כולו דרך מבוי,
kol hayom kulo derech mavoi, even if he's using his front door
the entire day for like, you know, for bringing in like, you
know have moving trucks coming in and out the whole day, camels
and wagons, so clearly his main use is the front door,
nevertheless
אינו אוסר פני מבוי, eino oser pnei mavoi, he's not a problem
anymore. Why? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? בפתחא דמייחד ליה, Bepsitcha demayachad lei,
in his private back door, because the back door opens up into
like a private space as opposed to the front door that opens
up into the courtyard, בה ניחא ליה. bah nicha lei. So he
prefers it. Now this seems like a complete פיקציה fiktzia right? Because
the whole point is even if you're using your main door. But
we'll see in a minute the גמרא Gemara didn't consider it a
total פיקציה. fiktzia. But it's basically saying we can say that you
as a non-Jew you've got a back door and that's your primary
you know sort of means of coming in and out and of
carrying and the space you use your house uses, right, what's the
problem of the non-Jew? He's considered somebody that has rights in the
courtyard and because he can't participate in the עירוב eiruv his rights
are creating a problem. So we're going to say you effectively you
really you know the space you use is your backyard. So therefore
you never really exert your rights in the courtyard and therefore you're
not a problem. And therefore you know so you're going in and
out of?
He
is right here he's got his house on the street, okay, let's
consider that this is the חצר chatzer or whatever. I'm just trying
to make it more like us. And then he's got a back
he's got a back door and he's got himself a big yard
in the back. So even though the whole day he's got moving
vans coming in and out and he's using his main front door,
we say
he really doesn't use the courtyard. He really uses his backyard. You
have a door to the backyard, your private backyard, that's your space,
so you really aren't creating a problem in terms of the courtyard.
Now that would seem to be a total פיקציה, fiktzia, but the
גמרא Gemara now continues in the following way which seems to take
it seriously, or maybe anyway. איבעיא להו, Ibaia lehu, they asked the
question: פתוח לקרפף מהו? Patuach lekarpef mahu?
Let's say it's not open into a big wide valley, it's open
into a קרפף, karpef, which is basically also like an open space
but it's surrounded by walls, but it's not as huge as like
a valley. Okay. So what's the story there? Would we say the
same thing, that's his back door. yard? So אמר רב נחמן בר
אמי משמיה דעולא, amar Rav Nachman bar Ami mishmei d’Ulla, אפילו פתוח
לקרפף, afilu patuach l’karpef, even if it's open to a קרפף, karpef,
that works. Okay, now, the fact that it's asking the question shows
that maybe the Gemara assumed that it was a reality, right, that
he really does prefer his backyard. So it says let's say it's
not as big of a backyard. Okay, now the answer though might
be that no, it's a fiction and we maintain the fiction even
if it's a smaller backyard. Okay, so it's interesting if the Gemara
thinks that it's a reality or a fiction. It's certainly easier to
see it as a fiction.
I don't understand why they would maintain the fiction. He doesn't use
that door but it's not a problem?
Because that's what I mean by a fiction. Since in theory, since
he's got a backyard and he has a door to the backyard,
we're going to say the same way we say when the non-Jew
isn't around he's not a problem, so even when he is around,
if he's got a nice big backyard and he could in theory
use it, we're going to say that's his primary space and it's
like he's not in the courtyard. That's what I mean by a
fiction. It's not really true in terms of the facts. Okay, so
anyway, so רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו, Rava v’Rav Yosef d’amri tarvaihu,
now Rava and Rav Yosef put a limit on it. They both
say בית סאתיים נוכרי בית סאתיים אוסר. beit satayim nochri beit satayim
oser.
If his backyard is just a בית סאתיים beit satayim or less,
which you remember a קרפף karpef surrounded by בית סאתיים beit satayim
which is five thousand square אמה, amah, which is not so big.
So it's about, what is it? It's about a hundred feet by
a hundred feet. Okay, ten thousand square feet, which sounds big. But
anyway, a hundred feet by a hundred feet is not so big.
Anyway, if it's that size or smaller, it's considered a רשות היחיד,
reshut hayachid, right? If it's that size or bigger, יותר מבית סאתיים
yoter m’beit satayim that’s לא הוקף לדירה, lo hukaf l’dirah, that’s surrounded
with walls and not seen primarily as sort of like a domicile
or for the purpose of, you know, of habitation, rabbinically is considered
a כרמלית. karmelit. So the בית סאתיים beit satayim line is some
type of a line between how much is it considered to be
a real like, you know, extent, a real like sort of private
domain or how much is it considered to be like a wide-open
space? If it's too big of a wide-open space, we can't consider
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So that's what they're saying. If it
is, I'll start with the second case, יותר מבית סאתיים, yoter m’beit
satayim, a nice big wide-open space, then it's not a problem. However,
if it's בית סאתיים, beit satayim, if it's small and considered normally
like a, you know, domicile type of a space, then it's not
a backyard type of space. Backyard is an open space, okay? And
therefore, if it's בית סאתיים, beit satayim, we cannot use this fiction
and he creates a problem. Now תוספות Tosafot actually makes it better.
תוספות Tosafot says if it's
בית סאתיים, beit satayim, what would we call a בית סאתיים beit
satayim in, you know, halakhically, surrounded by walls? Okay, it's a רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid, right? So if it's a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid,
it's all just his house. It's not his backyard. So that's sort
of the way, you know, one way of thinking about it. Okay,
the Gemara though did not say explicitly surrounded by walls, not surrounded
by walls. Anyway, but the basic point here is yes, as long
as the space is big enough, we'll have this fiction that that's
his real space. But after it gets to be a certain small
size, we no longer say that he basically uses his backyard.
What’s the difference? It’s his backyard anyway.
I know, but within the fiction, we have to be able to,
that's exactly אדרבה, aderaba, the whole point that we make a distinction,
not in practice how much is he using it, but in terms
of halakhic categories means we’re making a fiction. So as long as
you consider it just a yard, we’ll say he uses it. But
once you consider it to be like a type of a domicile,
then we can’t say he uses it as a, you know, as
a, as a, as a tradeoff, you know, as a substitute for
the courtyard. So that’s the whole point of being a fiction is
that because it's a fiction we’ll say it in certain cases and
not in others because in one we can more hypothetically put it
into that category.
Yeah, but that changes, you know, that was back then where people
had a lot more space. What about these days?
So again, that’s the idea of this being a fiction, you know,
is that it’s not based on the reality question. So let’s take
a look at now as the Gemara continues. So that’s point number
one. If he’s got something which we would consider to be a
decent backyard, yes, but if it's less than בית סאתיים, beit satayim,
if it’s בית סאתיים beit satayim or smaller, no, then we cannot
claim that it's a substitute, it's a substitute for the חצר. chatzer.
Now the Gemara says like this and interesting, an interesting sort of
irony
here. בישראל, B’Yisrael, now if it's a ישראל Yisrael that he has
an opening to the קרפף karpef and to the מבוי mavoi and
he let’s say he forgot to participate, right? The ישראל Yisrael who
forgot is similar to the non-Jew. So here we get the
reverse. בית סאתיים אינו אוסר יותר מבית סאתיים אוסר. beit satayim eino
oser yoter m’beit satayim oser. That בית סאתיים beit satayim does not,
a בית סאתיים beit satayim does not create a problem, more than
a בית סאתיים beit satayim does create a problem. Why? Because if
it's a ישראל Yisrael and it's more than a בית סאתיים, beit
satayim, we’ll call this more than a בית סאתיים, beit satayim, what's
its status? Assuming לא הוקף לדירה. lo hukaf l’dirah. What halakhically can
you carry in it? No. Because if this is more than, if
this is more than a בית סאתיים, beit satayim, it's greater than
five thousand whatever, square אמה, amah, okay, יותר מבית סאתיים yoter m’beit
satayim and it's not הוקף לדירה, hukaf l’dirah, so it's basically it's
a רשות... reshut... rabbinic כרמלית. karmelit. Biblically it's a רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid, but it's a כרמלית karmelit and you can't carry. So, if
that's what he's got for his backyard as a כרמלית, karmelit, so
now he creates a problem for the courtyard. Why? Because if his
backyard is a כרמלית karmelit and on שבת, Shabbat, the only space
he could use is the courtyard space, assuming it makes an עירוב.
eruv. So he actually does have a presence in the courtyard. If,
however, he's got less than בית סאתיים, beit satayim, right? So then
he's got a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid space to use in the
backyard, and we could say he prefers his private space to the
public space and he uses it. But the only question you've got
is that wait one minute, is that like why do we say
the Jew is happy with a small space, a backyard that's בית
סאתיים, beit satayim, and the non-Jew is not?
רש״י Rashi says because the Jew wants to carry in it.
Well,
yeah, but the non-Jew also wants to carry in his own way.
He says the non-Jew needs a lot more space on שבת. Shabbat.
שבת Shabbat for him is Saturday. For the Jew, it's שבת, Shabbat,
so he doesn't need such a big space. That's at least what
רש״י Rashi says. But anyway, you've got that interesting irony about the
non-Jew creating the problem and the Jew creating the problem not having
made an עירוב, eruv,
and the idea is can we say they're not around because they're
using the backyard? The answer is the reverse. The non-Jew, the bigger
the space is, we say he uses the backyard. The Jew, if
it's too big, he can't use the backyard, so it's actually the
reverse.
But if it is הוקף לדירה? hukaf ledira?
If it is הוקף לדירה, hukaf ledira, then according to תוספות, Tosafot,
it can never help because then it's an extension of the house.
Then it's considered part of the house. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. בעי מיניה רבא בר חקלאי מרב הונא. ba'ei
minei Rava bar Haklai meRav Huna. So רבא בר חקלאי Rava bar
Haklai asked רב הונא. Rav Huna. פתוח לכרפף מהו? patuach lecharpaf mahu?
So how about if the נוכרי, nochri,
meaning he asked the same question, okay? Like the person we had
before when the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב נחמן בר אמי משמיה
דאופנא. amar Rav Nachman bar Ami mishmei de-Ofna.
By the way, I didn't mention then that רש״י Rashi says אופנא
Ofna is not the name of a person, it means teaching like
a traditional teaching. So he just had that traditional teaching. Anyway, so
the exact same point we made before in a כרפף karpaf and
בית סאתיים beit satayim was asked here in another context, didn't know
the other tradition. So אמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Ulla amar
Rabbi Yochanan. Where were we? So בעי מיניה רבא בר חקלאי מרב
הונא פתוח לכרפף מהו? ba'ei minei Rava bar Haklai meRav Huna patuach
lecharpaf mahu? What's the story if it's open to a כרפף? karpaf?
אמר ליה, amar lei, הרי אמרו. harei amru. So he told him
what we had just said a minute ago. בית סאתיים אוסר, beit
satayim oser, if it's small, a בית סאתיים, beit satayim, it's a
problem. This is the נוכרי nochri case. יותר מבית סאתיים אין אוסר,
yoter mibeit satayim ein oser, if it's bigger, then it's considered more
of a yard and therefore it's not a problem in the נוכרי
nochri case. אמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan.
Now, for a moment, we leave עירובין Eruvin or we leave the
types of עירובין Eruvin discussion we've been having, and we go more
to the שבת Shabbat discussions of just defining רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
So let's take a look. It's going to be obviously connected, but
a little bit of a conceptual shift. כרפף יותר מבית סאתיים שלא
הוקף לדירה. karpaf yoter mibeit satayim shelo hukaf ledira. This is what
I sort of said to you a minute ago. You have this
fenced-in yard, more than a בית סאתיים, beit satayim, more than 5,000
square אמות, amot, but it wasn't fenced in for the purposes of
habitation. Now as I've mentioned to you, what habitation means in this
context is not clear, you know, doesn't mean that somebody has to
be sleeping in that space. What type of use is considered use
to be הוקף לדירה? hukaf ledira? I mentioned to you that this
is one of the big issues for an עירוב, eruv, because for
an עירוב eruv to work, you cannot have a space within the
walls of the עירוב eruv that is יותר מבית סאתיים שלא הוקף
לדירה. yoter mibeit satayim shelo hukaf ledira. So very often, you know,
anytime that people sort of do walks through it, it could be
a park, you know, but people walk through the park, fine, that's
לדירה, ledira, they're using the park. But it becomes a problem when
it's space that people don't walk through, like it's a big lake,
you know, or something of that nature, that becomes a question of
how do you define הוקף לדירה. hukaf ledira. But anyway, so if
you have this type of a space, it's big and walled-in, but
it's very big and it's not specifically done for habitation. ואפילו כור
ואפילו כוריים, ve-afilu kor ve-afilu korayim, and even if it's huge, size
of a כור kor and כוריים, korayim, whatever that is, much larger,
הזורק לתוכו חייב. hazorek letocho chayav. But still biblically a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. Yes, rabbinically it's a כרמלית karmelit and you can't carry
in it, but biblically, no matter how big it is, as long
as it's surrounded by walls, it's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. מאי
טעמא מחיצה היא. mai ta'ama mechitza hi. It's really a wall. אלא
שמחוסרת דיורין, ela she-mechuseret diyurin, just nobody lives in it. It's not,
so no one lives in it is a rabbinic problem, but biblically
it's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay. It's, by the way, I
should mention it's a little bit ironic, because you know, if too
many people live in it, it becomes a רשות הרבים reshut harabim
or it's like the חצר chatzer problems. But if nobody lives in
it, it's more like just the wide outdoors. It stops being like
a, you know, a private domain. Okay. So he just emphasized that
this whole יותר מבית סאתיים yoter mibeit satayim issue is rabbinic. Biblically
it's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. מתיב רב הונא בר חיננא. metiv
Rav Huna bar Chinana. So רב הונא בר חיננא Rav Huna bar
Chinana asked on this. So it's actually quite fascinating that there seems
to be a question about this point that some, you know, at
one stage the גמרא Gemara here is going to suggest that maybe
it biblically is a כרמלית, karmelit, which is a fascinating
idea. It's not just about the architectural features. So I want to
point out that that's similar to the רמב"ם *Rambam*. You mentioned the
רמב"ם *Rambam* said for something to be רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim* it
has to be owned by the רבים *Rabim* and if it's privately
owned even if it's used as a mass thoroughfare it's not a
רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim*. So here the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* actually is
going to think maybe רבי Rebbe, יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is wrong, maybe
actually if it's too big and if it's big and people don't
live in it maybe it's not a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *Reshus
HaYachid* even דאורייתא de'oraisa. *D'oraissa*. So let's take a look. So מותיב
רב הונא בר חיננא *Motiv Rav Huna bar Chinena*. סלע שבים גבוה
עשרה *Sela she-bayam gavoah asara*. You have a rock in the middle
of the ocean or the sea whatever that's ten טפחים *Tefachim* high.
The ocean is a and the sea is a כרמלית carmelit *Karmelis*.
Ten טפחים *Tefachim* high and four by four טפחים *Tefachim* wide. אין
מטלטלין לא מתוכו לים ולא מהים לתוכו *Ein metaltelin lo mitocho layam
velo mehayam letocho*. So you can't travel you can't carry from the
from the sea onto the rock or from the rock onto the
sea because it's going from a כרמלית carmelit? *Karmelis* which is the
sea to the rock which is a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *Reshus
HaYachid*. פחות מכאן מטלטלין *Pachus mikan metaltelin*. If however the rock is
smaller or not as high you can carry because then it is
also a כרמלית carmelit *Karmelis*. Now כרמלית carmelit, *Karmelis* you can't carry
ארבע אמות arba amos. *arba amos* but there's no problem of crossing
the line. So basically you've got your right?
You've
got your rock here surrounded by the nice sea. So this is
a כרמלית carmelit, *Karmelis*
and this is a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *Reshus HaYachid*. So you
can't even do one step over that line because you can't go
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *Reshus HaYachid* to a כרמלית carmelit, *Karmelis*. It's
like רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *Reshus HaYachid* to רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim*.
You also can't go רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim* to a כרמלית carmelit
*Karmelis*. כרמלית carmelit *Karmelis* is the worst of both worlds. Okay but
if this is a כרמלית carmelit *Karmelis* then you can't go ארבע
אמות arba amos *arba amos* but the stepping over the line is
not the problem and therefore you can put it right in the
sea right next to it. Okay so okay אין מטלטלין לא מתוכו
לים ולא
מהים לתוכו
*ein
metaltelin lo mitocho layam velo mehayam letocho* ואמרת *ve'amrat* פחות מכאן מטלטלין
*pachus mikan metaltelin* עד כמה *ad kama* until how until when is
this true עד בית סאתים beis saitayim, *ad beis sasayim* until it's
בית סאתים beis saitayim *Beis Sasayim* big. More than בית סאתים beis
saitayim *Beis Sasayim* if the rock is bigger than בית סאתים beis
saitayim *Beis Sasayim* then it's different. So what's different? So now that's
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to analyze. אהייא *Ahai* on
which case of this is at is does the idea of bigger
than בית סאתים beis saitayim. *Beis Sasayim* make a difference. אילימא אסיפא
*Ileima aseifa* on the last case when the rock is when the
rock is small and it's a כרמלית carmelits *Karmelis*. בית סאתים *Beis
Sasayim* טפי לא *tvei lo* so and more than בית סאתים *Beis
Sasayim* wouldn't והא כרמלית carmelit לכרמלית קא מטלטל *veha karmelis lekarmelis kametaltel*.
If this is less than ten טפחים *Tefachim* this is nine טפחים
*Tefachim*. So who cares if the rock is a בית סאתים *Beis
Sasayim* it's a huge rock. It's still a כרמלית carmelit. *Karmelis* right?
So why shouldn't you be able to step over the line? The
basic point is it's כרמלית carmelit. *Karmelis* to כרמלית carmelit, *Karmelis* so
it cannot when it says that more than בית סאתים *Beis Sasayim*
is a problem it cannot be the case where the rock is
a כרמלית carmelit *Karmelis*. That should not create a problem. אלא לאו
ארישא *Ella lav areisha* it's going on the first case. והכי קאמר
*Vehachi ka'amar* סלע שבים גבוה עשרה ורוחב ארבעה *Sela she-bayam gavoah asara
verochav arba* if it's ten by four it's a רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid *Reshus HaYachid* אין מטלטלין לא מתוכו לים ולא מהים לתוכו *ein
metaltelin lo mitocho layam velo mehayam letocho*. You can't go from it
to the ocean and back and forth. ועד כמה *Vead kama* when
is this true that this restriction applies עד בית סאתים *ad beis
sasayim* if it's only בית סאתים *Beis Sasayim*. היתר מבית סאתים *Hayeser
mibeis sasayim* meaning if it's bigger than that מטלטלין *metaltelin* you could
carry. So what is it saying? You've got this it's ten טפחים
*Tefachim* this it's a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *Reshus HaYachid* don't cross
this line okay. That's a red line I'm gonna make it a
red line. Don't cross that line it's a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
*Reshus HaYachid*. But once it gets to be יותר מבית סאתים yeser
mibeis saitayim, *yoser mibeis sasayim* then what happens? The רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid *Reshus HaYachid* becomes a כרמלית *Karmelis* right? Because it's יותר מבית
סאתים yoser mibeis saitayim *yoser mibeis sasayim* and then you can cross
the red line. Okay but one minute according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* it's still biblically a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *Reshus HaYachid* it
just has the restrictions of a כרמלית *Karmelis*. It's a rabbinic added
rabbinic restriction but it's still biblically a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *Reshus
HaYachid*. Why are you allowed to cross the line? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this אלמא כרמלית היא
*alma karmelis hee* you see it's a full כרמלית *Karmelis* you're allowed
to do a קולא kula? *kula*. תיובתא דרבי יוחנן *Tiyuvta de-Rabbi Yochanan*
that's a challenge on רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. So אמר רבא Rava
*amar Rava* so רבא Rava's *Rava* says מאן דלא ידע לתרץ מתניתא
תיובתא מותיב ליה *man d'lo yada litaratzei masnisa tiyuvta motiv lei* a
person who doesn't know how to explain a ברייתא braita *Braisa* you're
going to ask a question based on it? So first understand the
ברייתא braita. *Braisa* then you can ask use it as a question.
תיובתא מותיב ליה *Tiyuvta motiv lei* לרבי יוחנן *le-Rabbi Yochanan* לעולם ארישא
*le'olam areisha* you are right it's going on the first case.
But he's
saying this to רב הונא בר חיננא *Rav Huna bar Chinena* that
used this as a challenge לרבי יוחנן *le-Rabbi Yochanan*.
You don't know what you're talking about.
Yeah you don't know what you're talking about you've misunderstood the ברייתא
Baraisa, *Braisa*. לעולם ארישא *Le'olam areisha* you're right it's going on the
first case but it doesn't mean that if it's bigger than בית
סאתים *Beis Sasayim* you can cross the line. Here's what it means.
והכי קאמר *Vehachi ka'amar* when it says that you can carry you
can't cross the line from the rock to the ocean implicit is
yes you can't cross the line from the rock to the ocean
but
הא בתוכו *ha bitocho* implicit in the ברייתא *Braisa* is
מטלטלין *metaltelin*. implicitly is though, but it’s okay to carry on the
rock. And then it says and by the way, when is that
true that you can carry on the rock? עד בית סאתים, but
bigger than בית סאתים, it’s a Rabbinic כרמלית and you can’t carry
on it. Okay, so by the way, his read of the ברייתא
is not so persuasive that he should have that type of a
response, like you don’t even know how to read the ברייתא. But
that’s what he says. It just means bigger than that you can’t
carry on the rock, that’s all it means. רב אשי אמר לעולם
הרישא. Rav Ashi amar le'olam areisha. רב אשי Rav Ashi says, and
I was expecting you to say this Michael, רב אשי Rav Ashi
says no, no, no, actually his read is correct, that when it’s
bigger than בית סאתים you are allowed to go from the rock
to the ocean. How do we have a קולא? Because הן אמרו
והן אמרו. hein amru vehein amru. By the way, that’s a great
little phrase that expresses a lot of what goes on in the
גמרא. Gemara They’re making up the rules! So they said and they
said. Meaning, like a pesha or a pesher? Who says you’re not
allowed to cross the line from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, to a
כרמלית? That’s Rabbinic. כרמלית doesn't mean anything biblically. So they said don’t
cross the line. When they turned this into a כרמלית, it is
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, but when they gave it the restrictions
of a כרמלית, so they they said Rabbinically you can’t carry in
this space, but now that we’re calling it a כרמלית, in order
to be consistent, we’ve got to allow you to go over the
line. So we'll waive that restriction, it’s only a Rabbinic restriction to
begin with. Okay? הן אמרו והן אמרו. hein amru vehein amru.
So then you can do it from one כרמלית to another.
So you can go from a כרמלית to a כרמלית even if
one of the כרמלית is really רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, Okay. And
now it’s going to explain it all, explain it. הן אמרו: hein
amru: קרפף יותר מבית סאתים שלא הוקף לדירה אין מטלטלין בו אלא
ארבע אמות. karpaf yoser mibeis saitayim shelo hukaf ledira ein metalttelin bo
ella arba amos. They said if you’ve got this huge space, then
even though it’s technically רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, you can only carry
within ארבע אמות. arba amos? So that’s a pure Rabbinic כרמלית added
on the biblical רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, והן אמרו, vehein amru, but
they also said don’t cross the line: אין מטלטלין מרשות היחיד לכרמלית.
ein metalttelin mereshus hayachid lekarmelit. So don’t cross the line from רשות
היחיד to a כרמלית. בית סאתים דשרי לטלטולי וכולי. beis saitayim desharei
letaltulei vechulei. If it’s בית סאתים or less, that it’s fully expressing
itself as a real as a רשות היחיד, you’re
allowed to carry in it. So אסרו רבנן לטלטולי לא מן הים
לתוכו ולא מתוכו לים. asru rabbanan letaltulei lo miyam letocho velo mitocho
leyam. That’s when the Rabbis held the line. Don’t carry from רשות
היחיד to a כרמלית. That’s when it’s fully expressing itself as a
רשות היחיד and you’re allowed to carry in it. מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? רשות היחיד גמורה היא. reshus hayachid gemura hi. It’s a full
רשות היחיד, so don’t cross that line. יותר מבית סאתים, yoser mibeis
saitayim, once it’s bigger than בית סאתים דאסרו לטלטולי וכולי, de'asru letaltulei
vechulei, that they don’t let you carry in it Rabbinically, right? They
say now it’s too big, so Rabbinically you can’t carry in it.
שרו רבנן לטלטולי מתוכו לים ומים לתוכו. sharei rabbanan letaltulei mitocho leyam
umiyam letocho. They let you cross the line. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
Why? Why don’t we just add give it both restrictions? What’s the
need of waiving the other for consistency? So the answer is: דילמא
אמרי רשות היחיד גמורה היא, dilma amri reshus hayachid gemura hi, because
if what’s going to happen, if you’re inconsistent? So you got this
huge thing of יותר מבית סאתים and let's say we’re going to
not let you cross the line. So if we not let you
cross the line, the only reason you’re not allowed to cross the
line is because you’re telling me it’s a רשות היחיד. So basically
what you’re telling me is this thing is a really רשות היחיד,
it’s really רשות היחיד, I’ll carry in it. Okay?
So which I would be allowed to do biblically, if not Rabbinically.
So the question is why do we Rabbinically prefer one גזירה gezera
over the other? That’s what we’re going to get to. דילמא אמרי
רשות היחיד גמורה היא, dilma amri reshus hayachid gemura hi, if you
hold the line, you’ll make me think it’s a real רשות היחיד,
ואתי לטלטולי בכוליה, ve'asi letaltulei dechulei,
and I’ll come up carrying the whole thing. So now the גמרא
Gemara. says: ומאי שנא? u'mai shna? Okay, but your one of these
Rabbinic things is going to have to go. Okay? Because, so
why do you hold on to the איסור issur to carry on
the rock and you’re willing to waive the problem of the line?
Why not the reverse? So the גמרא says: תוכו שכיח, tocho shchi'ach,
because carrying in the space is the more common scenario, wanting to
carry within this big rock space and the entire space of the
בית סאתים. מתוכו לים ומים לתוכו לא שכיח, mitocho leyam umiyam letocho
lo shchi'ach, because
so at the end of the day, crossing the line, you can
only go, right, less than ארבע אמות anyway. So basically if we
have to maintain one of these גזירות, gezeirot, basically it’s a question,
when we have the יותר מבית סאתים, right, that’s לא הוקף לדירה,
lo hukaf ledira, so רשות היחיד, but we’re Rabbinically calling it a
כרמלית, what’s more important? Like to say go ahead and carry in
it, but that’ll stop you from crossing the line? How often is
it that we have to worry about crossing the line less than
ארבע אמות? No, our primary גזירה gezera is we don’t want you
carrying in it, that’s our focus, that’s what’s going to happen most
of the time. So we hold, in order to hold this, we’re
going to have to let you cross the line. And that’s what,
and that’s and that’s why we say that we can actually, it
still is biblically רשות היחיד, but it’s Rabbinically a כרמלית and we’re
just actually being consistent. All right. So now the גמרא goes on
to another case, also a little bit off sort of figuring a
real world case which is quite important in terms of הלכות שבת.
Hilchos Shabbos. So let's take a look.
ההוא ינוקא דאישתפוך חמימי, hahu yanuka de'ishtapich chamimei, there was a child
that they had to do a ברית מילה bris milah for and
they would use hot water, you know, for רפואה refua purposes, health
purposes after the ברית, bris, and the hot water was spilled. And
now they needed to get hot water. Okay, the only problem is
that the hot water was in one of the houses and the
ברית מילה bris milah was taking place in another house, or was
taking place in the courtyard. So you have to carry from you
know through the courtyard and we'll see they didn't make an עירוב
eruv and it's going to be a problem. Now before we get
to that תוספות Tosfos says this is only that the ברית מילה
bris milah hasn't taken place yet. Once the ברית מילה bris milah
took place, then it's פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. Okay, but it hasn't
taken place yet. So what can you do to allow the ברית
מילה bris milah to take place to make sure you have the
hot water that you need? So אמר ליה... amar lei... אמר ליה
רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said to them, the people
in the courtyard, נייתו ליה חמימי מגוא ביתאי, naisu lei chamimei migov
beisai, it was רבא Rava courtyard. So רבא Rava said, go bring
them hot water from my house, I have... I have hot water
we can use. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye
said, והא לא ערבינן, veha lo arvinnan, but we didn't make an
עירוב, eruv, which by the way is fascinating. Number one, that רבא
Rava didn't realize they didn't make an עירוב. eruv. Number two is,
why are they not making an עירוב? eruv? You got a courtyard,
why are you not making an עירוב? eruv? Anyway, אמר ליה, amar
lei, נסמוך אשיתוף. nismoch achituf. Oh, no problem, because there's going to
be an opinion later on that even if the courtyards don't make
an עירוב, eruv, if they... if the courtyards got together to make
a שיתוף מבואות, shituf mevo'os, right, then you don't that... then you
don't have to make an עירוב. eruv. בדיעבד bedieved you can rely
on that. Right? Remember that's the common sort of scenario here, which
is you've got all of the courtyards, right, with their houses, right,
opening up into a מבוי. mavoi. Okay, so they... these usually do
an עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros and then these all do it together,
right, to do a שיתוף מבואות. shituf mevo'os. So there's an opinion
that if you just did the שיתוף מבואות shituf mevo'os without doing
the individual עירוב חצרות, eruv chatzeros, that that actually can work to
let you carry in the individual courtyards. So he said, well okay
fine, we'll just rely... we'll just rely on the שיתוף shituf that
we did. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבא Rava said back, והא
לא שפתינן. veha lo shaftinnan. We didn't do that either!
It's so funny, you know, A: how did רבא Rava's not know,
and B: why aren't they doing it? Okay, so then רבא Rava...
said fine, here's what we'll do. He's just spending his whole שבת
shabbos learning, he doesn't get his mind into these things. נימרה ליה
לנוכרי ליתי ליה. namelei lenochri leiselei. So tell a non-Jew to bring
it. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, בעי לאוסופי
למר, ba'ei le'osfai lemar, I wanted to challenge this, to ask... ask
something on this... on his suggestion. ולא שבקן רב יוסף, veloch shavkan
Rav Yosef, but רב יוסף Rav Yosef was there, who was אביי
Abaye and רבא Rava רבי, and he said shhh, shut up, just...
we'll talk later. Okay, so he wouldn't let me ask רבא... אביי
Abaye my question...
wait, רבא or רבה? Rabba? This was רבה. Rabba.
Oh this was רבה. Rabba. I'm sorry, you're right, this was רבה,
Rabba, right. So actually רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef were
colleagues, אביי Abaye was the תלמיד. talmud. So רב יוסף... Rav Yosef...
so אביי Abaye said I wanted to challenge רבה, Rabba, and רב
יוסף Rav Yosef said, you know, said don't do, don't do it.
Like you know, whatever. Let's go... let's go ahead with it. So
דאמר רב יוסף אמר רב כהנא, de'amar Rav Yosef amar Rav Kahana,
'cause רב יוסף Rav Yosef said in the name of רב כהנא,
Rav Kahana, כי הוינן בי רב יהודה, ki havinnan bei Rav Yehuda,
when we were in the house of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, הוי
אמר לן, havi amar lan, he told us the following important principle.
בדאורייתא, bide'oraisa,
if it's a biblical matter at stake and there's a debate, are
you allowed to do something or not allowed to do something, מותבינן
תיובתא והדר עבדינן מעשה. mosvinnan tiyufta vehadar avdinan ma'aseh. First we challenge
it, we raise all the challenges before we act on it. It's
a... it's a דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So if you've got any question to
raise, raise it. בדרבנן, biderabbanan, if it's a rabbinic matter at stake
and there's some discussion and somebody says we should be allowed to
do it because of XYZ, and you have some
question, עבדינן מעשה והדר מותבינן תיובתא. avdinan ma'aseh vehadar mosvinnan tiyufta. Go
ahead and act on it, you know, and then we can challenge
it and then we can discuss it. פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? Right,
it's exactly like we had before, you know, יפה סיידם ששכחת. yafeh
sidem sheshacharta. We're not exactly sure what the הלכה halacha is, but
we... we have a good argument, so go ahead and you do
it. At the end of the day, it's a דרבנן, derabbanan, so
and you know, if you've got an... if you've got a pressure
to act on it, so you act now and then you can
sort of analyze it later. In all דרבנן? derabbanan? No, he's saying
it in all דרבנן. derabbanan. Now he's not saying you could just
say, oh it's דרבנן derabbanan I assume it's מותר. muttar. He's saying
that you actually have come... somebody has actually articulated a position and
said I think that this should be מותר, muttar, I'm פוסק paskening
this way. Just because you want to challenge the position, you know,
then hold off on your challenges and we can rely on that
to act. This in a way is less of a חידוש chiddush
than the other one. The other one is nobody knew what to
do. They said, yeah you could say this way, you could say
that way, let's just do it and we'll find out later. Here
you actually have some... are asserting a position and the point is
don't challenge it. Okay, so אביי Abaye was quiet.
לבתר הכי, lebasar hachi, after the whole story took place, אמר ליה,
amar lei, so then רב יוסף Rav Yosef turned to אביי Abaye
and said, נו, nu, מה בעית לאוסויי למר, mah ba'is le'osai lemar,
what were you going to challenge רבה? Rabba? Let's hear it now.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, דתניא, detanya, because we taught in a
ברייתא, הזאה שבות, hazah shevus, ואמירה לנוכרי שבות. ve'amirah lenochri shevus.
So... so he says look, he says um, you know, sprinkling ashes
of a פרה אדומה parah adumah is rabbinically forbidden. And telling a
non-Jew is rabbinically forbidden. Now whoever talked about sprinkling ashes for פרה
אדומה? parah adumah? Because if ערב פסח erev Pesach falls on a
שבת shabbos and you're טמא, tamei, and the only way you'll be
able to bring your קרבן פסח korban Pesach is if we sprinkle
the ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah on you, and then you'll
be able to eat your קרבן פסח korban Pesach when it comes
nightfall, we do not sprinkle the ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah
on you. And you can't... and you're not able to do your
קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. So by rather, so to not do a
דרבנן, d'rabbanan, we'd rather not do a דרבנן d'rabbanan than have, I
mean we choose keeping the דרבנן d'rabbanan over you doing this מצוה
mitzvah of bringing the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach even though it's a
מצוה שיש בו כרת. mitzvah sheyeish bo kares. Okay. So if that's
true, we should say the same about a non-Jew and a ברית
מילה. Bris Milah. Let's keep the איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan and we'll
do the ברית מילה Bris Milah on a different day. And by
the way,
you can do ברית מילה Bris Milah אדרבה. adaraba. First of all,
basically, it's interesting, ברית מילה Bris Milah and פסח, Pesach, and maybe
the reason for comparison is those are the two מצות עשה שיש
בו כרת. mitzvos asei sheyeish bo kares. But on the other hand,
I think it's an even better argument to wait. ברית מילה Bris
Milah at least you'll do tomorrow, so it's not בזמנו. bizmano. Okay.
So, so מה זאת? ma hazos? So if you look at the
top of ס"ח עמוד א. samech cheis amud aleph.
That's what I just said.
I know you have פסח שני, Pesach Sheini, but I think it's
still, if you had the choice, would you rather do a מילה
שלא בזמנו milah shelo bizmano or פסח שני? Pesach Sheini? מילה שלא
בזמנו Milah shelo bizmano seems less of... but פסח שני Pesach Sheini
is you missed it, it's a makeup. You know, מילה שלא בזמנו
milah shelo bizmano is just you're a little bit late. Okay, not
a little, I mean obviously there's... Anyway, that's, things should be the
question. מה הא הזאה שבות? Ma haza shvus? The same way as
הזאה hazas is rabbinically forbidden and אינה דוחה שבת, einah dochas Shabbos,
we don't override שבת Shabbos just in order to do that. אף
אמירה לנוכרי שאינה דוחה שבת. Af amira lenochri she'einah dochas Shabbos. So
even אמירה לנוכרי. amira lenochri. So it's, you know, that, by the
way, I gotta tell you, thank God that position did not take
hold because אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri is a huge way in which
we deal with situations of שעת הצורך sha'as hatzorech on שבת. Shabbos.
There's questions what threshold you need, you know. Is it שני דרבננים?
shnei d'rabbanans? Is it צורך מצוה, tzorech mitzvah, מצטער, mitzta'eir, חולה? choleh?
But basically, thank God we didn't follow אביי Abaye who wanted to
sort of say אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri never, you can never violate
it for the, you know, it always, you always have to maintain
אמירה לנוכרי. amira lenochri. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so here's what
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said back to him. ולא שני לך בין
שבות דאית ביה מעשה לשבות דלית ביה מעשה? Velo shani lach bein
shvus d'is beih ma'aseh l'shvus d'leis beih ma'aseh? You don't see a
distinction between a rabbinic prohibition that has an action versus one that
does not have an action? דהאמר לא אמר לנוכרי זיל אחים ליה?
D'ha'amar lo amar lenochri zil achim lei? You didn't tell him heat
up the hot water. Now I have to say a few, wait,
no this is רב יוסף's Rav Yosef's response to אביי. Abaye. רב
יוסף's Rav Yosef's response why you, it was okay to tell the
non-Jew. Now this is a very important halachically how to parse this
response. Okay? The simple,
first of all, if you don't include the half of the line
after דהאמר d'ha'amar after the little א. aleph. The basic response is
there's a difference. One is a שבות דאית ביה מעשה, shvus d'is
beih ma'aseh, sprinkling the ashes is אית ביה מעשה. is beih ma'aseh.
Why would you say אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri is לית ביה מעשה?
leis beih ma'aseh?
Because you're not doing...
you're just verbally doing it and the one that's actually doing the
physical act is the non-Jew. So that makes you much more removed
from it, so that's a weaker thing and therefore it's allowed. Now
that idea that an אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri is a weaker דרבנן
d'rabbanan in the sense of the threshold to make it allowed because
it's לית ביה מעשה leis beih ma'aseh plays out a lot when
it comes to issues, for example, of you know, שעת הצורך sha'as
hatzorech and particularly health issues. Like a חולה שאין בו סכנה, choleh
she'ein bo sakanah, what are you allowed to do? So there are
some that say that you can do any איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan
for a חולה שאין בו סכנה, choleh she'ein bo sakanah, and there
are others that say no, you can just do אמירה לנוכרי. amira
lenochri. That אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri is a special lenient category because
of לית ביה מעשה, leis beih ma'aseh, it's just verbal. So but
now we פוסקים pasken basically you can do almost, you know, any
דרבנן d'rabbanan for a חולה שאין בו סכנה, choleh she'ein bo sakanah,
I mean broad strokes, whatever. But exactly this idea that אמירה לנוכרי
amira lenochri is easier to allow in שעת הצורך sha'as hatzorech because
of לית ביה מעשה, leis beih ma'aseh, that's one parsing of the
גמרא. The other...
and the other parsing however adds in the words דהאמר לא אמר
לנוכרי זיל אחים ליה. d'ha'amar lo amar lenochri zil achim lei. The,
which means what? You didn't tell him to heat up water. Meaning
so it's לית ביה מעשה leis beih ma'aseh because even the non-Jew
didn't do a real act. But what do you mean? The non-Jew
carried. So what's the point? But carrying, this whole thing is a
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. זיל אחים Zil achim is a דאורייתא. d'oraisa? And this
way what he's saying is it wasn't just an אמירה לנוכרי. amira
lenochri. It was an אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri on an איסור דרבנן,
issur d'rabbanan, what's called שבות דשבות. shvus dishvus. So it's a double
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Ah, therefore that's allowed. And that leads to this other
whole discussion which is צורך מצוה, tzorech mitzvah, which is what this
is, what is allowed with צורך מצוה? tzorech mitzvah? So the general
consensus is a שבות דשבות, shvus dishvus, a דרבנן d'rabbanan of a
דרבנן d'rabbanan like this, a double דרבנן. d'rabbanan. But there's, there is
a position of the בה"ג Bahag that even one דרבנן, d'rabbanan, even
אמירה לנוכרי. amira lenochri. Because he doesn't have this last line. So
it's really this little response of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. First of
all, thank God we think like אביי Abaye because אמירה לנוכרי, amira
lenochri, as I said, is the major way we deal with a
lot of צורך מצוה tzorech mitzvah and מצטער mitzta'eir and צורך tzorech
on שבת, Shabbos, number one. But number two is, number two is
what is the point of distinction that רב יוסף Rav Yosef is
making? Is it that אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri is weaker because it's
only אמירה, amira, which would mean other דרבננים d'rabbanans need a higher
threshold? Or is his point that it's weaker because it's a double
דרבנן, d'rabbanan, which would mean that even an אמירה לנוכרי amira lenochri
wouldn't be allowed if it was an אמירה amira on a דאורייתא?
So a lot of הלכות halachos hinge on this one response of
רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Okay. חג שמח Chag same'ach everyone. So a
lot of הלכות halachas hinge on this one response of רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. Okay, חג שמח chag sameach everyone. Who's this guy called?
Oh, I can't believe I just did this. I forgot. Oh well.